Guide to the Howard Fifield Legg Letters, 1900 - 1904
Howard Fifield Legg Letters, 1900 - 1904
Special Collections & Archives, Wesleyan University
Legg, Howard Fifield.
1000-173
0.5
1
Howard Fifield Legg (1881-1973), Wesleyan class of 1904, spent his career as a pastor and later a professor.
The Howard Legg Letters are about life on the Wesleyan University campus while Legg was a student between 1900 and 1904. Topics include sports, especially track and football; his membership in Delta Kappa Epsilon (DKE); and his many classes and activities.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
No restrictions
Acquisitions Information
Donated by Howard Fifield Legg in 1972.
Biographical Note
Howard Fifield Legg, born in 1881 in Rhode Island, spent his childhood in Worchester, Massachusetts. Legg graduated from Wesleyan University in 1904 and went on to Drew Theological Seminary in New Jersey (1904-1907). Beginning in 1906, he was a student pastor and then after graduating from the seminary, he was a pastor in New England until 1925. From 1922-1925, he was a student at the Boston University Theological and Religious Education graduate program. From 1925 to 1936, he was a professor of religion at Evansville College, and then at Simpson College in Iowa from 1936-1946. In 1946, he retired to California with his wife, Nellie.
Collection Overview
These letters were handwritten while Legg was a student at Wesleyan (1900-1904) and kept by Legg's mother. In 1907, when Legg married, he and his wife, Nellie, typed them up and they were kept in storage until his wife died in 1968. At that point, many of the letters has been eaten by silverfish. In 1972, at the age of 92, Legg went through the half-eaten letters and added some notes and tried to fill in the missing information. The typed transcripts are 175 pages with the letters filling the pages.
The Howard Legg Letters are about life on the Wesleyan University campus while Legg was a student between 1900 and 1904. He wrote about life as a freshman, such as trying to become a member of Delta Kappa Epsilon, as well as his his classes and the work that came with them. He was on the track team and wrote about the practices and meets. Legg was interested in the other athletic achievements of the university, especially when his friends were part of them, particularly the football team. He was a member of various campus groups and described his activities. For the most part, the letters specifically to his father are more business-like than those to the whole family or just his mother. He often mentioned finances in the letters to his father. While it is only mentioned in the very last letter in the collection, Legg delivered a speech, The Sense of Responsibility, at his commencement ceremony, but the text is not included in this collection of letters.
Collection Arrangement
The letters are organized chronologically by date.
Online Catalog Headings
These and related materials may be found under the following headings in online catalogs.
Legg, Howard Fifield.; Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)--History.; Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)--Sports.; Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)--Students.; Delta Kappa Epsilon. Gamma Phi Chapter (Wesleyan University, Middletown, Conn.); Legg family.
Detailed Description of the Collection
  - Biography and chronology (Folder 1)
  - Letters home from college, typed transcripts from 1900 to 1904. (Folder 2)
    The following list includes the date of each letter and the page in the transcript it is on, as well as to whom the letter was written. The actual letters are not part of the collection, but the text of all of them are included in the transcripts.
    - Page 1, first letter home
    - Page 7, October 1, 1900: to Mother
    - Page 7a, October 8, 1900: to Folks at Home
    - Page 9, October 10, 1900: to Father
    - Page 10, October 14, 1900: to Folks at Home
    - Page 13, October 15, 1900: to Father
    - Page 15, October 19, 1900: to Mother
    - Page 15, October 22, 1900: to Folks at Home
    - Page 16, October 28, 1900: to Folkses
    - Page 20, November 4, 1900: Dear Folkses
    - Page 23, November 11, 1900: Dear Everybody
    - Page 25, November 18, 1900
    - Page 29, November 22, 1900: Everybody
    - Page 30, December 9, 1900
    - Page 32, December 17, 1900: Dear Folkses
    - Page 33, January 6, 1901
    - Page 34, January 13, 1901
    - Page 34, January 20, 1901: Dear Folkses
    - Page 36, January 27, 1901: Dear Folkses
    - Page 38, February 3, 1901: Dear Folkses
    - Page 40, February 10, 1901: Dear Everybody
    - Page 42, April 8, 9 10, and 14, 1901
    - Page 44, April 21, 1901: Dear Folkses
    - Page 45, April 23, 1901: My dear Mother
    - Page 46, May 1, 1901: Dear Mama
    - Page 47, May 12, 1901: Dear Mama
    - Page 48, May 14, 1901: Miss Bessie W. Legg
    - Page 48, May 19, 1901
    - Page 50, May 20, 1901: Dear Mama
    - Page 50, May 26, 1901: Dear Folkses
    - Page 53, May 29, 1901: Dear Mama
    - Page 53, June 2, 1901: Dear Folks
    - Page 55, June 8, 1901
    - Page 55, June 9, 1901: Dear Folks
    - Page 57, June 16, 1901: Dear Folks
    - Page 58, June 17, 1901: Dear Pappa
    - Page 59, June 20, 1901: Mr. John Legg
    - Page 59, June 23, 1901: Dear Folks
    - Page 61, September 22, 1901: Everybody & Co.
    - Page 61, September 30, 1901: Dear Folks
    - Page 64, October 6, 1901: Dear Folks
    - Page 67, October 13, 1901: Dear Folks
    - Page 70, October 16, 1901: Dear Papa
    - Page 70, October 20, 1901: Dear Folks
    - Page 72, undated: Dear Papa
    - Page 72, November 3, 1901: Hello Everybody at Home
    - Page 73, November 17, 1901: Dear Folks
    - Page 75, November 24, 1901: Dear Folks
    - Page 78, December 8, 1901: Dear Folks
    - Page 79, December 13, 1901: Dear Mama
    - Page 80, December 15, 1901: Dear Folks
    - Page 81, January 12, 1902: Dear Ones at Home
    - Page 84, January 14, 1902: Dear Papa
    - Page 84, January 19, 1902: Dear Folkses
    - Page 85, January 28, 1902: Dear Folkses
    - Page 88, February 2, 1902: Dear Folks
    - Page 90, February 9, 1902: Dear Folks
    - Page 91, February 10, 1902: Dear Papa
    - Page 91, February 16, 1902: Dear Folks
    - Page 92, March 2, 1902: Dear Folks
    - Page 95, March 9, 1902: Dear Folks
    - Page 96, March 16, 1902: Dear Folks
    - Page 97, March 23, 1902: Dear Folks
    - Page 99, April 6, 1902: Dear Folks
    - Page 103, April 2, 1902: Dear Folks
    - Page 104, April 20, 1902: Dear Folks
    - Page 105, April 28, 1902: Dear Papa
    - Page 105, May 4, 1902: Dear Folks
    - Page 107, May 11, 1902: Dear Folks
    - Page 110, May 18, 1902: Dear Folks
    - Page 111, May 25, 1902: Dear Folks
    - Page 112, May 27, 1902: Dear Mama
    - Page 112, May 28, 1902: Dear Papa
    - Page 113, June 1, 1902
    - Page 114, June 15, 1902: Dear Folks
    - Page 115, June 26, 1902: Dear Folks
    - Page 115, June 29, 1902: Dear Folks
    - Page 116, June 28, 1902: Dear Papa
    - Page 116, July 1, 1902: Dear Mama
    - Page 118, September 21, 1902: Dear Folks
    - Page 119, September 23, 1902: Dear Mama
    - Page 120, October 19, 1902: Dear Folks
    - Page 120, December 1, 1902: Dear Mama
    - Page 121, December 1, 1902: Dear Mama
    - Page 121, December 14, 1902: Dear Folks
    - Page 122, January 12, 1903: Dear Folks
    - Page 123, January 18, 1903: Dear Folks
    - Page 123, January 25, 1903: Dear Folks
    - Page 124, February 1, 1903: Dear Folks
    - Page 125, January 29, 1903: Dear Mama
    - Page 127, February 5, 1903: Dear Mama
    - Page 127, February 8, 1903: Dear Folks
    - Page 128, February 15, 1903: Dear Folks
    - Page 129, February 23, 1903: Dear Mama
    - Page 131, March 5, 1903: Dear Mama
    - Page 132, March 1, 1903: Dear Folks
    - Page 133, March 8, 1903: Dear Folks
    - Page 134, March 9, 1903: Dear Mama
    - March 19, 1903: Dear Father
    - Page 135, March 15, 1903: Dear Folks
    - Page 136, March 22, 1903: Dear Folks
    - Page 137, March 29, 1903: Dear Folks
    - Page 138, April 25, 1903: Dear Folks
    - Page 139, May 3, 1903: Dear Folks
    - Page 140, May 10, 1903: Dear Folks
    - Page 141, May 18, 1903: Dear Mama
    - Page 142, May 24, 1903: Dear Folks
    - Page 142, May 31, 1903: Dear Folks
    - Page 143, April 5, 1903: Dear Folks
    - Page 144, May 17, 1903: Dear Folks
    - Page 144, June 7, 1903: Dear Mama
    - Page 145, June 14, 1903: Dear Father
    - Page 146, June 28, 1903: My dear mother and father and brother
    - Page 147, September 13, 1903: Dear Mother
    - Page 149, September 20, 1903: Dear Mother
    - Page 149, September 27, 1903: Dear Mother
    - Page 149, October 4, 1903: Dear Mother
    - Page 152, October 18, 1903: Dear Mother
    - Page 152, October 25, 1903: Dear Mamsie
    - Page 153, November 1, 1903: Dear Mother
    - Page 154, November 8, 1903: Dear Mother
    - Page 155, November 16, 1903: Dear Mother
    - Page 156, November 22, 1903: Dear Mother
    - Page 156, November 29, 1903: Dear Mother
    - Page 157, December 6, 1903: Dear Mother
    - Page 158, December 13, 1903: Dear Mother
    - Page 158, December 20, 1903: Dear Mother
    - Page 159, December 21, 1903: Dear Mother
    - Page 159, January 10, 1904: Dear Mother
    - Page 160, January 17, 1904: Dear Mother
    - Page 161, January 24, 1904: Dear Mother
    - Page 163, January 31, 1904: Dear Mother
    - Page 164, February 28, 1904: Dear Mother
    - Page 164a, February 12, 1904: Dear Mother
    - Page 165, March 13, 1904: Dear Mother
    - Page 165, March 20, 1904: Dear Mother
    - Page 167, April 10, 1904: Dear Mother
    - Page 168, April 17, 1904: Dear Mother
    - Page 169, April 24, 1904: Dear Mother
    - Page 170, May 8, 1904: Dear Father
    - Page 171, May 15, 1904: Dear Father
    - Page 171, May 13, 1904: Dear Mother
    - Page 171, May 24, 1904: Dear Mother
    - Page 172, May 29, 1904: Dear Mother
    - Page 173, June 5, 1904: Dear Mother
    - Page 174, June 12, 1904: Dear Mother
    - Page 174, June 19, 1904: Dear Mother
    - Page 175, The End
  - Photocopies of all 175 pages of the typed transcripts in folder 2 (Folder 3)